Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Socialist Labor Party PE.028
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Socialist Labor Party
1883-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.028
2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) (1883-1992) is an artificial collection of materials assembled by the Tamiment Library, which was founded in 1906 as the library of the Rand School of Social Science, and is a special collection documenting the history of United States radicalism, labor, and progressive social action. Tamiment Library staff accumulated printed ephemera through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, organizations, bookstores, and other collecting activities. This collection consists of fliers, leaflets, newspaper clippings, memoranda, reports, pamphlets, publications, and other printed ephemera created by the Socialist Labor Party, a Marxist political party founded as the Socialistic Labor Party in 1877.
Historical Note
The Socialistic Labor Party, originally organized as the Workingmen's Party in 1876, was founded in 1877. The name was changed to Socialist Labor Party (SLP) in 1890. The official publisher of the Party was the New York Labor News Company, and many pamphlets from publisher exist in this collection as well as in the Tamiment cataloged books and pamphlets collections. Two histories of the organization are included in the collection. The SLP was a Marxist organization and still exists today. In the late 1800s the Party attempted to affiliate with union and labor groups to create one large organization and then tried to move members away from the American Federation of Labor, which failed. Those who were involved in this movement later were part of the founding of Industrial Workers of the World (I.W.W.). Daniel DeLeon was a major figure in the party. Pamphlets by and about him are part of the collection and can also be found in the Tamiment cataloged books and pamphlets collections.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Socialist Labor Party (1883-1992) and consists of fliers, newspaper clippings, brochures, circular letters, pamphlets, convention proceedings, and reports. Clippings and flyers pertaining to candidates and the party platform make up a significant part of the collection. Also included are materials from the National Executive Committee, meeting minutes, publications, and circular letters. A few state and local party records are included in the collection. The main SLP papers collection is housed at the University of Wisconsin.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Party (U.S.) Printed Epehmera Collection PE 032
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Arrangement
Untitled files are arranged chronologically, followed by titled files arranged alphabetically.
Clippings (information artifacts); Brochures.; Fliers (printed matter); Pamphlets.; Socialism -- United States.; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914; Socialist Labor Party; Socialistic Labor Party (U.S.)
- 1883-1896 (Box 1)
- 1897-1902 (Box 1)
- 1911-1912, undated (Box 1)
- 1977-, undated (Box 1)
- Beginners' Study Material, 1961-1967 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1900-1920 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1924-1928 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1932-1940 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1944-1950 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1956-1961 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- Candidates and Platform, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Candidates: Brandon, Joseph, 1925 (Box 1)
- Circular Letters, 1934-1957, undated (Box 1)
- Constitution, 1916-1976 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1920, 1924 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
- Convention, 1983 (Box 1)
- Fliers, 1947-1965 (Box 1)
- Fliers, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
- Fliers, undated (Box 1)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This folder contains access copies of the fragile originals found in the next folder.
- Fliers, undated (Box 1)
  Materials in file are fragile originals. Access copies are available in the preceeding folder.
- Fliers, undated (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 14)
- Fliers and Brochures, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
- Fliers and Brochures, 1981-1992 (Box 1)
- History: 40 Years: Four Decades of the Socialist Labor Party 1890-1930 (Box 1)
- History: Golden Jubilee 1890-1940 (Box 1)
- Industrial Unionists, 1906-1927 (Box 1)
- International Congress - Stuttgart, Germany, 1907 (Box 1)
- Membership: Brochures, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
- Memoranda I, 1944-1949 (Box 2)
- Memoranda II, 1944-1949 (Box 2)
- National Executive Committee, 1921-1926, undated (Box 2)
- National Executive Committee: Manifesto, 1920-1922 (Box 2)
- National Executive Committee: Minutes, May 5, 1923 (Box 2)
- National Executive Committee: Publications, 1919-1942 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company, 1894-1980 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Capitalism, 1921-1955, undated (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: DeLeon, Daniel, 1933-1963 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Socialism, 1900-1978 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Stalinism/Russia, 1927-1978 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Various I, 1916-1978 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Various II, 1916-1978 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: War, 1936-1961 (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Women, undated (Box 2)
- New York Labor News Company Pamphlets: Workers/Labor, 1919-1978, undated (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1918-1976 (Box 2)
- Organization and Work (of Party), 1925-1928 (Box 2)
- The Party Press, 1900-1904 (Box 2)
- Publication: Socialist Studies I, 1976-1984 (Box 2)
- Publication: Socialist Studies II, 1976-1984 (Box 2)
- Socialist Democratic Party, 1900, undated (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: American Section - St. Louis, MO, 1893 (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Connecticut, 1897, undated (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Hungarian Federation, undated (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Massachusetts, undated (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Michigan, 1970 (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Minnesota, Minneapolis Section, 1897 (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Minnesota, St. Paul Section, 1896 (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party: Pennsylvania, undated (Box 2)
- Socialist Labor Party - Rhode Island, 1900 (Box 2)
- Socialist Party, undated (Box 2)